<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: mvc | Daniel Chang]]></title>
  <link href="http://danielchangNYC.github.io/blog/categories/mvc/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://danielchangNYC.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-04-09T11:16:39-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://danielchangNYC.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Daniel Chang (couchpanda / c0depanda)]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[daniel.chang85@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[ActiveRecord]]></title>
    <link href="http://danielchangNYC.github.io/blog/2013/10/08/rails-presentation-post/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-08T07:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://danielchangNYC.github.io/blog/2013/10/08/rails-presentation-post</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I took a bit of a dive today and looked a Ruby on Rails <a href="http://www.slideshare.net/aizatto/ruby-on-rails-48391">presentation</a>. Here&rsquo;s what I gleaned from looking through all the slides.</p>

<ul>
<li><p>Rails is a web application framework that allows your Ruby to interact with the web seamlessly. By &ldquo;interact with the web&rdquo;, I assume the presentation means &ldquo;interact with databases.&rdquo;</p></li>
<li><p>Rails implements a principle called &ldquo;MVC&rdquo; &mdash; Model View Controller. Rails seems to handle each task separately. I&rsquo;m going to focus on the Model, which uses ActiveRecord.</p></li>
<li><p>ActiveRecord is a Module that Rails uses to model and interact with databases. It makes database queries both simple and intuitive.</p></li>
</ul>


<p>Here are some concrete query comparisons between using SQLite3 versus Rails' ActiveRecord.</p>

<p>Assume we have a table called &ldquo;dogs,&rdquo; each with a name, age, weight, and type. Each attribute would be a column, and each row would represent a different dog.</p>

<p><code>sql Table using SQLite3
CREATE TABLE dogs (
  id INTEGER PRIMARY KEY AUTOINCREMENT,
  name TEXT;
  age INTEGER;
  weight INTEGER;
  type TEXT
);
</code>
We can also imagine this as a class of Dog objects in Ruby. Here&rsquo;s how one might create the barebones structure in Ruby.
<code>ruby Dogs as objects of class Dog in Ruby
class Dog
  attr_accessor :id, :name, :age, :weight, :type
end
</code>
<code>ruby Table initialized using Rails' ActiveRecord
class Dog &lt; ActiveRecord::Base
end
</code></p>

<p>See how simple that was? Now we can make queries on the table.</p>

<p><code>sql SQLite3 query for first dog in table
SELECT * FROM dogs WHERE id=1;
</code>
<code>ruby Rails query for first dog in table
Dog.find(1)
</code></p>

<p>That&rsquo;s just the beginning! Check this out.</p>

<p><code>sql SQLite3 query appending conditions
SELECT * FROM dogs WHERE age=8 AND type="corgi";
</code>
<code>ruby Rails query appending same conditions
Dog.find_by_age_and_type 25, "corgi"
</code></p>

<p>It seems like ActiveRecord must use certain keywords like &lsquo;by&rsquo; and &lsquo;and&rsquo; in order to dynamically use the attribute names that the user inputs.</p>

<p>What is really beautiful though is the idea of &ldquo;configuration of convention&rdquo; that Rails implements in order to shorten the amount of code you need to write. Slides 42-44 of the <a href="http://www.slideshare.net/aizatto/ruby-on-rails-48391">presentation</a>  gave a particularly good example of the idea. No wonder people love Rails!</p>

<p>The slides continue talking about the MVC</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
